YWCA of the U.S.A. Records. Record Group 3. National Administrative Office
Sophia Smith Collection
- SERIES II. BUILDINGS AND PROPERTIES
  The logistics of administering an operation that was at such a distance from headquarters, as well as the financial burdens of staffing and maintaining such a facility, were always somewhat challenging for the shrinking national staff. Part of the National Association's renewed emphasis on leadership training included, as part of Member Association accreditation, required attendance at training sessions in Phoenix. At least some cash-strapped Community Associations objected to the expense involved in traveling to Arizona for training that had previously been offered regionally. The Leadership Development Center was sold circa 2000 to a private "conferencing" firm as part of the major restructuring of the National Association.
  Rising Manhattan real estate prices and shrinking national staff led the National Board to finally agree to sell its headquarters at 600 Lexington Ave. in the early 1980s. Headquarters made use of rented spaces in New York City until the major reorganization in 1999-2000, when it relocated and joined the Washington, DC Office staff.
  Altamont (Millbrook, NY): a 90-acre estate donated to the National Association in 1959 and 1960 by Nancy Boyd Sokoloff for use as a conference center. The gift was accepted on an experimental basis with the option to sell the property if, after two years, that was deemed expedient. The experiment was extended somewhat, but it was eventually determined that the property was not "in the mainstream" of the Association's work and it was sold in 1964.
  Asilomar Conference Grounds (Pacific Grove, California): When the site of previous YWCA western region summer conferences burned in 1912, Phoebe Apperson Hearst (mother of William Randolph Hearst) persuaded the Pacific Improvement Company (now the Pebble Beach Co.) to donate thirty beachfront acres to the YWCA for the development of a western conference center. The YWCA hired San Francisco architect Julia Morgan in 1913 to design the buildings. The winning entry in a 1913 contest for naming the property, was a combination of two Spanish words, 'asilo' meaning retreat or refuge, and 'mar' meaning ocean. In 1917, Ellen Browning Scripps purchased an additional 20 acres for the property. By 1921, Asilomar was a year-round facility able to accommodate 500 people. Asilomar was never a self-supporting endeavor and the financial challenges of the Great Depression led the National Board to vote in 1934 to sell it. No buyer appeared, so California YWCA "leaders" formed an Asilomar Committee to oversee the facility. It was leased for some years, used for military housing during World War II, and opened as a full-service conference facility in 1947. The property was again offered for sale in 1951 and fear of development of the prime site eventually prompted local residents to advocate for its preservation. The California Division of Beaches and Parks purchased the property in 1956. It is currently the Asilomar State Beach and Conference Grounds.
  Camps: though most YWCA camps were owned by Member Associations, the National Association owned a few of them over the years. [see Camping in Record Group 6]
  Chautauqua Hospitality House (Chautauqua, NY): Originally purchased for use during World War I, the House was run as a "Peace-Time Hostess House" and day nursery for visitors to the Chautauqua Institution. The Chautauqua County YWCA initially ran the house until 1921 when the National Association took over its management. A cafeteria and camping facilities were added, then an addition with dormitory rooms for female students and staff at Chautauqua. The Chautauqua Institution purchased the Hospitality House from the YWCA of the USA in 1965.
  Fletcher Farm (Proctorsville/Ludlow, VT): Mary E. Fletcher gave the farm and 500 acres to the National YWCA around 1929. It was used for several years as the home of the National YWCA Summer School. The program included seminars for staff, and meetings of nationality, town, and rural secretaries. The YWCA sold it circa 1933 and, as of 2007, it was the Fletcher Farm School for Arts and Crafts of the Vermont Society of Arts and Craftsmen, Inc.
  Grace Dodge Hotel (Washington, DC): Built with War Work Council money and given to the National Association in 1921, the Grace Dodge Hotel was intended to house girls and women working in Washington during World War I. Still under construction when the war ended, the YWCA of the USA decided to operate the hotel as a demonstration business, providing good working conditions for its employees in an industry where working conditions were generally very poor. The hotel was for women only until 1926, when it was opened to men and families in an effort to increase income. It proved to be a profitable venture, and the Association used money from its building depreciation fund to supplement the National Association's budget during the Great Depression. By World War II and its associated housing crunch, DC's unwritten policy against interracial hotels came to be an issue within the National Association. The membership did not want its name or the name of its first President associated with a segregated hotel. The YWCA sold the Hotel in 1959, and the building was razed circa 1972.
  Hollywood Studio Club see Series III in Record Group 8
  Leadership Development Center (originally known as Fleishmann Learning Center) (Phoenix, AZ): Dedicated in 1983, the LDC was a centralized, year-round, non-residential center for training of YWCA staff funded in part by a grant from the Max C. Fleishmann Foundation. The Center was sold, circa 2000, as part of major restructuring of the Association to Sodexho Conferencing, Inc. As of 2007, it is known as the Black Canyon Conference Center.
  National Headquarters and National Training School (New York City and Washington, DC): The first YWCA of the USA Headquarters was in the Hotel Montclair, 541 Lexington Ave at 49th Street in New York City, the site where the merger between the International Board of Women's and Young Women's Christian Associations and the American Committee of Young Women's Christian Associations had been negotiated in December 1906. In 1908, the YWCA joined the International Committee of the YMCA, the Student Volunteer Movement, and the Young People's Missionary Movement at 125 East 27th Street, in a building "expressly built" for those organizations by Mrs. William Dodge and Mrs. Russell Sage. During this period (1908-12), the National Association rented space for its training school and the school's administrative offices at 3 Gramercy Park, Gramercy Court on 22nd St., and 125 East 27th St.
  It became clear within two years that the two floors occupied by the YWCA in this building were inadequate. The Association put together a Committee on Future Headquarters to plan for a new building of their own. Built 1911-12 at the corner of Lexington Avenue and East 52nd St., it housed the national headquarters, with an entrance at 600 Lexington Ave., and "The Annex," with an separate entrance around the corner at 132/135 East 52nd St. The Annex initially served as the home of the National Training School with accommodations for resident students. The living spaces were later made available to non-students and became known as "The Residence." Since the idea was two separate entities within the one building, the committee which oversaw administration of the building was known as the "Buildings Committee" for many years.
  Designed with the latest ideas regarding "scientific management," the structure served as a model for association buildings. Helen Gould gave $200,000 to purchase the land and Grace Dodge and four others donated $665,569 for the building. It was the first national woman's building to be built in the United States solely for the use of a woman's movement, and the Headquarters Committee was formed to manage oversight of the property. The building, known affectionately as "600," was much loved by YWCA members across the country. After years of receiving offers to purchase such prime real estate, the National Board decided to sell the building in December 1981. The purchasers, London and Leeds Investments of Great Britain, demolished the building and re-developed the site. The Association invested the proceeds from the sale as part of a long-range financial plan, hoping that the additional endowment would facilitate maintenance of operations, and, with luck, allow for some expansion of national services.
  In 1982, the National office moved temporarily to 135 West 50th Street, then to 726 Broadway in 1984. This was followed in 1997, by a move to the Empire State Building (350 50th Ave.) and, in 2003, after a major reorganization, a consolidation of headquarters staff and the Washington office at 1015 18th St, NW, Washington, D.C.
  This series includes minutes, architectural plans, reports, correspondence, printed materials, newspaper clippings, and other administrative records (1908-96) related to various properties owned by the YWCA of the USA.
  Microfilmed Records, 1906-1970 only
  Most of the Buildings and Properties materials on the microfilm were discarded after filming. They include minutes and reports of committees in charge of planning the new headquarters building in 1910-12, and management of National Board headquarters, as well as records related to the management of the Grace Dodge Hotel and purchase and sale of miscellaneous properties.
  They can be found under:
  Asilomar Committee
  Buildings Committee [re management of National Association headquarters building]
  Future Headquarters, Committee on [planning of 600 Lexington Ave.]
  Dodge Hotel
  National Board, Building
  Real Estate
  Original Format Records, 1908-96, 4 linear feet
  [see Original Format Records Folder List]
  There is little overlap between the surviving paper records and the microfilmed Buildings and Properties materials.
  The paper records consist of general information, newspaper clippings, printed materials, minutes, reports, and other items primarily about the Asilomar Conference Grounds, the Leadership Development Center, and the National Board Headquarters with small amounts of materials on various other properties. The materials are arranged alphabetically. The bulk of the materials relate to the funding for and construction of the Leadership Development Center.
  Files about ongoing building maintenance at '600' are located in SERIES 1 of this Record Group
  Materials about the Hollywood Studio Club; consulting on building and swimming pool construction and maintenance; boarding houses, cafeterias, and shared YMCA-YWCA buildings can be found in RECORD GROUP 8. SERVICES TO COMMUNITY ASSOCIATIONS
  Information about summer camps and materials about World War I facilities are located in RECORD GROUP 6. PROGRAM
  There are many photographs of YWCA buildings in RECORD GROUP 9. PHOTOGRAPHS
  RECORD GROUP 10. AUDIO-VISUAL MATERIALS contains video from various events at the Leadership Development Center, including its dedication in 1982 and its 10th anniversary.
- SERIES III. FINANCE AND FINANCIAL DEVELOPMENT
  Financial management and fund-raising were initially handled by one office at the National Association. The Treasurer was an elected officer of the National Board. Day-to-day oversight of Association finances and accounting was carried out by staff of the Finance Department. (The Board of Trustees, which was responsible for real estate owned by the National Board and endowed funds, had its own Treasurer.) In the Association's early years, Grace Dodge, the first President of the National Association, routinely made up any budget deficit out of her own funds carrying the national work 'until it should be strong enough to carry itself.' After her death in 1914, the Association did not immediately make an organized effort at addressing regular budget problems and tended to make up the difference out of its endowed funds. The advent of World War I with its highly successful campaigns for war work funds and associated influx of money gave the Association large-scale fund-raising experience which was accompanied by similarly large-scale increases in program.
  War work 'Continuation' funds carried the Association through 1920, but the dramatic decrease in budget in 1921 necessitated a large cut in staff and reorganization of departments. The National Board's report to the 1922 Convention sated "we have passed through a period in which the sense of responsibility for finance remained largely undeveloped. Because Miss Dodge thought the need for national unity so urgent, the work was launched ahead of the slow growth of a financial constituency." The Finance Division, established in 1923, had responsibility for securing the National Board budget 'difference'; any special fund-raising effort; and service to Community Associations 'in method and training' through the Finance Service Bureau.
  The World Service Council, a committee of the Finance Division, was established after World War I to make use of the highly effective fund-raising capacity of the members of the War Work Council. Its goal was to secure substantial contributions from individuals to the national budget on a continuing basis. World Service Council members also participated in interpretation of the national work to the general public.
  Another staff reorganization, in 1932-33, separated the accounting/budget control functions from fund-raising, establishing as separate functions within General Administration a Comptroller's Office and a committee responsible for securing the funds necessary to meet the National Board's budget. It also transferred responsibility for advising Community Associations on financial matters to the newly formed National Services Division. The committee, known by 1933 as the Committee on National Support and Interpretation, was charged with directing all efforts for raising money through gifts from individuals, funds, and foundations; securing quota payments from Community Associations; promoting endowments and bequests; and interpretating the work of the National Association to the public.
  The National Association had three sources of funds: earnings from income-producing units (such as the Grace Dodge Hotel, and sales of publications), income from endowment, and 'contributions' consisting of quota payments from local assns and gifts from individuals, foundations, and other sources. The term "National Support" was used to describe all types of 'contributions' to support the National Association.
  The National Board assessed its National Support needs in light of its anticipated budget and expectation of income from other sources, then set an amount to be made up in quota payments from Community Associations. The amount due from each Association was determined according to formulas devised by the Committee and calculated based on an Association's overall budget, the membership dues it received, and various other contributions. Though quota payments were mandatory, some Associations took the obligation much more seriously than others and there were no serious consequences if an Association did not meet its quota.
  The Comptroller's Office continued to perform budget control and accounting functions as part of the main administrative office through the rest of the century, changing name to Finance Department in 1986.
  Financial Development had a more varied administrative history, sometimes combined with Public Relations and Publications and sometimes not. Between 1933 and 1948, the work was managed by the Committee on National Support and Interpretation with the aid of the World Service Council. The sheer number of pages in the Committee's minutes and reports taken up by discussions of quota payments from Associations implies that their time and attention was primarily consumed by that aspect of their work.
  Financial difficulties caused by the Great Depression were temporarily alleviated during World War II. Special war-time programs and activities were well-funded by large cooperative campaigns. With the nation focused on the war, regular YWCA programs and fund-raising were more-or-less put on hold as had been the case during the First World War.
  As the National Association made adjustments after the war, its program for financial development came to seem inadequate and behind the times. It was clear that the National Association could not continue to rely on its endowment to cover deficits. The landscape of potential funding sources had changed with the increase in prevalence of community chests and councils. Such shared funds required very different types of appeals.
  In 1947 a Committee on Financing the National Board asked the John Price Jones Corporation to make a study of public relations, publicity, and fund-raising. Citing in particular the necessity of skilled and focused fund-raising and public relations efforts, the Jones report called for making National Support and Public Relations into departments, staffed by trained professionals rather than a committee with volunteer leadership. It also urged the National Association to make quota payments from Community Associations compulsory with serious consequences for non-compliance. Though the language related to quota payments changed, it was not until 1992 that the Association made a Community Association's continued affiliation with the YWCA of the USA contingent upon full payment of its quota.
  The National Support Department worked on yearly and special appeals, including periodic capital campaigns; cultivated large individual donors for gifts and bequests; devised National Support quotas for Community Associations; kept abreast of opportunities for grants and shepherded grant proposals initiated in the departments; and provided training for Community Associations in all of these areas.
  Over the years, the National Association had regularly received special and grant funding for targeted projects, such as the Rural Studies funded by the Ford Foundation and the Parker bequest for support of a music program in the 1920s. The reduction in national program activities after World War II made such short-term projects more the norm and tied together fund-raising and program in a different way. Instead of studying a situation to determine needs and then develop program to meet those needs, program proposals were more likely to be tailored to potential funding sources. The National Support Department helped various YWCA departments apply for and administer funding for such projects. When U.S. Government funding for 'War on Poverty' programs became available as a result of the Economic Opportunity Act of 1964, the YWCA entered into a relationship with the consulting firm Research and Action, Inc., to keep track of the funding legislation for social programs, coordinate proposals and reports, and maintain liaison with government agencies.
  Two studies (1958 and 1964) by Greenleigh Associates Management Consultants brought about another reorganization of the national office. Advising and training on financial matters was returned to the duties of the financial management and development staff in 1964 under a new unit, called Financial Resources Development (later Financial Development.) Beyond its regular activities, the new unit was intensely involved in major fund-raising events such as YWCA anniversary celebrations in 1983 and 1993-94, and two capital campaigns, Fund for the Future in the 1980s and Millennium 2000 in the late 1990s. New opportunities were created, such as the Tribute to Women in International Industry (TWIN) awards dinners.
  The World Service Council continued its regular support and also raised funds for special causes, such as the International Building Fund and continued staffing of the National Board Archives after budget cuts forced it to close in 1992.
  Included here are general files on three independent financial organizations founded for the benefit of YWCA employees: the Emissarius Credit Union, established in 1924 open to employees of the YWCA of the USA; the YWCA Retirement Fund, established in 1924 for the benefit of employed officers of the YWCA of the USA "when they shall retire"; and the YWCA Savings and Security Plan for Non-Secretarial Employees, established in 1940 for clerical and maintenance employees of the YWCA of the USA 'who faithfully render the supporting services which make possible the operation and expansion of the program and services of YWCAs, wherever they are.'
  Accounting/Budget Control functions:
  1907-23 Finance Committee/Department
  1923-25 Comptroller's Office, Finance Division
  1925-circa 1991 Comptroller's Office, General Administration
  circa 1991- Finance Department, Operations Division
  Financial Development functions:
  1923-33 Finance Division
  1933-48 Committee on/for National Support and Interpretation/Interpretation and Support, General Administration
  1948-63 Department of National Support, General Administration
  1964-71 Office of Financial Resources Development, General Administration
  1972-83 Financial Development
  1984-circa 1991 Financial Development Division
  c. 1991- Financial Development, Development and Public Relations Division
  This section contains correspondence, minutes, reports, financial statements, training materials, scrapbooks, publications and other materials related to the offices and committees charged with accounting/budget control and fundraising (including the financial obligations of the Community Associations to the national YWCA.)
  Included in this series is a small amount of material about the Emissarius Credit Union, YWCA Retirement Fund, and YWCA Savings and Security Plan for Non-Secretarial Employees all of which were independent organizations established for the benefit of YWCA employees.
  Financial development publications, created with publicity staff, chronicle the formation of the Association's public image while minutes, reports, and studies reveal struggles to articulate the mission of such a complex and, in many ways, flexible organization. The basic mission-to serve young women-took many forms over the years.
  Minutes, reports, and studies document the many challenges of financing the Association whether the result of outside forces, such as the Great Depression or the public criticism of the Red Scare years, or of the women's inexperience and, perhaps, women's reluctance to ask for funds from donors.
  They are also revealing of the nature of the relationship between the National Association and its member Associations. They record regular discussions about how to get Community Associations to make their quota payments and debates about whether or not the National Association should force Community Associations to make membership in the YWCA (with its associated fees) a requirement for all program participants.
  Though surviving records of earlier capital campaigns are modest in scope, there are substantial materials from the Fund for the Future (1980-86) and Millennium 2000 Campaign (1996-2000).
  Training materials, publications, and the visitation reports of secretaries document the training functions of the department.
  Microfilmed materials include minutes and reports of various committees; correspondence with banks, large contributors, foundations, and World Service Council members; information about funds and endowments; some financial development materials, general information about scholarship funds and national support; and some budget and financial statement materials.
  Finance and Financial Development materials can be found on the microfilm under:
  Corporation and Foundation Support Committee
  Endowment Committee
  Finance Committee
  Financial Resources Development Committee